Finding aid for the Getty Education Institute for the Arts, Grant Files, 1984-2001 IA10021
Institutional Records and Archives
- District grants, 1984-1992; I.; 10.75 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
  - District Grant Administration
    - District Grant Coordination Meetings:
      - January 1987:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Reports of Grant Coordinators (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Notes/Agenda/List of Attendees (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - April 1998:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Reports of Grant Coordinators (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Notes/Agenda/List of Attendees (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - District Grant Meeting, April 1988 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
    - Planning Grant Review, 1985-1986:
      - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - Guidelines for Review (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - Reviewers' Comments (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - List of Planning Grant Applications (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - List of Rejected Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
    - Implementation Grant Review, Spring 1987:
      - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - Guidelines for Review (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - Reviewers' Comments (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
    - District Implementation Grant Study:
      - Initiation:
        - District Implementation Grant Study (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Loose Papers (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Correspondence with Eisner/Walker (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Contract/Proposal – Eisner/Walker May 26, 1988 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Cross-Site Evaluation Report, February 1989 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Cross-Site Evaluation Report, May 1989 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
      - Year Two:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Correspondence with Clark & Hurwitz (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Contract/Proposal (Clark & Hurwitz), June 12, 1990 (Box 2007.IA.16-17)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
        - Final Survey/Curriculum Analysis Report (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
        - Interoffice Memos & CC's (Letters) (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
        - Contract/Proposal (Eisner & Walker) (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
        - Contract/Proposal (Eisner & Walker) (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
        - Correspondence with Eisner & Walker (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
        - [Loose Eugene, Oregon Reports] (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
      - District Grant Evaluation: Continuation (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
      - District Grant Program for 1992, Memo and Evaluation Report (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
      - [Project Materials, loose files and reports] (Box 2007.IA.16-18)
- Regional Institute grants, 1986-2001; II.; 61 Linear Feet (64 boxes)
  In the fall of 1986, wanting to encourage the adoption of DBAE by a critical mass of school districts across the country and seeking a means to encourage new forms of DBAE, the GEI initiated the Regional Institute Grant Program. The Regional Institute Grants (RIGs) were intended to replace the District Grant Program by supporting the planning and execution of DBAE staff development and curriculum implementation programs. The new grants were intended for projects with the following criteria: those proposing a 3-5 year program, comprised of both staff development and curriculum implementation components, and consisting of a consortium of universities, art museums, school districts, and other education and arts organizations. There were no limits on the geographic areas to be included in the grant proposals or the number of participating school districts. The first Regional Grants were awarded in 1987, when planning grants of $20,000 were given to eight consortial Institutes: Florida, Minnesota, Nebraska, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, Tennessee, and Texas. Pennsylvania and Rhode Island withdrew their applications after this first year, and the remaining six were awarded implementation grants of $125,000 a year for five years. To leverage local support for the Regional Institutes, each program was expected to raise matching funds of 50% the first year, 75% the second year, and 100% in years three through five. Additionally, Dr. Brent Wilson was asked to develop a five-year evaluation study for the regional institute projects. Additional assistance was provided in the form of offering regular meetings, seminars, networking opportunities, technical assistance, and grants for student assessment. The participant's progress was monitored through regular directors' meetings, student assessment projects, interim evaluation reports, and site surveys.
  By the summer of 1992 the RIGs were operating 16 satellite institutes, as well as their central institutes, and serving 11 states, expanding into publication and video projects, as well as teleconferences and collaborations with other regional institutes. They had found funds to match $1.61 for each Getty dollar and were working with over 200 school districts. The GEI considered the project highly successful and, faced with the fact that Florida, Ohio, and Tennessee were about to complete their fifth and final operating year in the Spring of 1993, chose to invite the Institutes to apply for strategic planning grants to design a second grant phase which would include a Core Program for veteran districts and National Specialty Programs that built on an acquired expertise in specialized areas.
  Evaluation of the Regional Institutes from 1988-1993 focused on organization and management, professional development programs, research and development efforts in DBAE theory and practice, the emerging conceptions of DBAE in the sites, and the effects of the programs through observing DBAE programs in schools and museums. Evaluator Dr. Brent Wilson was joined by Blanche Rubin in 1993 and, in 1994, the evaluation focus shifted to gathering qualitative and quantitative data on the implementation of DBAE in over 380 participating school districts.
  A number of changes in the RIG program occurred in fiscal year 1995, with the initiation of the second grant phase. Three separate small institutes operating in California under different guidelines and funding merged into a single Institute and began operating under RIG operating guidelines. Simultaneously, the GEI ceased funding the Minnesota project since it was unable to raise the required matching funds for the second consecutive year. Also during that year the grantees began offering redesigned programs to educators from veteran districts. The programs, called "Core/Maintenance," were intended to provide school personnel with introductory and advanced staff development opportunities in DBAE theory and practice, technical assistance for implementation, and networking opportunities. Grantees also began offering seminars to national audiences based on specialty areas related to DBAE. Such National Specialty Program seminars were initially offered by Nebraska, Ohio, Tennessee, and Texas; California and Florida followed after FY 1995.
  In 1996 the Regional Institutes formed the National Arts Education Consortium (NAEC) In 1997 NAEC was awarded a $4.3 million five-year grant from the Annenberg Foundation for a project called "Transforming Education Through the Arts Challenge" (TETAC) to work intensively with 18 schools to demonstrate how DBAE linked to school restructuring could contribute to improved student performance. The GEI provided $2 million of the $4.3 million required matching funds, specifically $1 million in new funds and $1 million in FY96-FY2000 core and national specialty grants.
  As the Annenberg grant took shape, the GEI, based on the Annenberg grant requirements and on a RAND corporation research project it had commissioned, chose to refocus the RIGs. The RIG directors were convened in an effort to ensure that by the projected program end date (FY 2001) a number of elements would be in place, specifically: 1) elementary, middle, and high schools that had institutionalized DBAE; 2) qualitative and quantitative data documenting the impact of the Regional Institutes and DBAE on participating students, teachers, and schools. To reach these goals, the Institutes chose to focus their efforts on 36 schools that agreed to institutionalize DBAE, serve as national demonstration sites, and participate in the program and student assessment study. The Institutes would continue to offer networking and professional development opportunities to those committed schools not chosen to be one of the 36. To provide additional support to the project, the Institutes agreed to adopt common standards and practices informed by the best practices developed over the last nine years, forming a steering committee and six inter-institute task forces to facilitate this adoption. Evaluations and assessments were planned for all aspects of the Institutes' work.
  In 1997-1998 the GEI phased out the National Specialty Program aspect of the Regional Institutes due to its limited success in attaining program goals and the need to redirect a portion of the funds to the Getty/Annenberg project. It also required the Institutes to develop leadership succession plans (as Institute leaders were showing signs of burn-out after ten years). A report summarizing the findings and conclusions of the first seven years of Regional Institute activites was published in 1997, called "The Quiet Evolution: Changing Faces of Arts Education" by Dr. Brent Wilson.
  The remaining years of the Regional Institute Grant Program were considerably quieter, given the 1998 decision of the Getty Trust to dissolve the Getty Education Institute. The projects were simply seen to conclusion under the general oversight of the Getty Grant Program.
  Records cover the planning, implementation, evaluation, and general administration of the Regional Institue Grant program managed by the Getty Education Institute for the Arts (GEI) from 1986 to 2001. Each of the recipient consortia and their work on discipline-based arts education curriculum implementation are represented in the grant files, as are the GEI's assessment, review, and evaluation processes. All stages of grant awards and the fulfillment of the grant requirements for various stages of planning, implementation, assessment, and evaluation are covered in detail. Vicki Rosenberg is the Getty staff member who figures most prominently in the files, though memos and correspondence from Program Director Lani Duke and Trust President Harold Williams are also present. Types of documents found in the records include correspondence, memoranda, notes, proposals, reviews and evaluations, reports, contracts, minutes, photographs, and agenda that range in date from 1986 to 2001.
  The records have been divided into four sections, which include one for Regional Institute grant recipients, one for Regional Institute reviews and evaluation, one for Regional Institute administration, and one for the secondary phase of the project with the Annenberg Foundation.
  The regional grant recipients are in alphabetical order by the name of the consortium and each has subsections for the planning and, where applicable, implementation, strategic planning, and assessment phases of their grants. The implementation phase is frequently subdivided by year and then by core vs. national specialty programming.
  The review and evaluation section is in rough chronological order with subdivisions for planning and implementation reviews and for the overall multi-year evaluation project.
  The administration area is more loosely organized but still subdivided into sections that include regional institute meetings, general correspondence and administration, student assessment grant administration, technical assistance grant administration, and national specialty program development.
  The final section concerns the Annenberg Foundation grant (Transforming Education Through the Arts Challenge) and the consortium formed by the regional institutes which was awarded the grant. It includes specific sections on the consortium, evaluations, and marketing.
  - Regional Grant Recipients
    - California Consortium for Visual Arts Education:
      - Strategic Planning Grant:
        - Budget/Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - California Regional Institutes: Correspondence prior to 1994 (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - [Loose: Lesson Plans: Central California Institute for Education in the Visual Arts] (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Sacramento County Office of Education, Alice Furry, [original grant award letters], 1993-1994 (Box 2009.IA.38-02)
      - Sacramento County Office of Education:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Budget, October 1994 (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Original Award Letters, 1994-1998 (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
      - Maintenance, Fiscal Year 1995:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Grant Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - October Progress Report (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - December Progress Report (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - April Progress Report (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Collateral Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Summer 1995 Institute Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
      - Maintenance, Fiscal Year 1996:
        - Grant Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Planning Grant Report, May 1996 (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - October Progress Report (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - December Progress Report (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - April Progress Report (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
      - Maintenance, Fiscal Year 1996:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
        - Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-55)
      - Core Program, Fiscal Year 1997:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Original & Revised for Year 1997 Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Interim Reports (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
      - Fiscal Year 1998:
        - Supplemental Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Supplemental Grant Guidelines (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Supplemental Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Core Program Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Core Program Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Core Program Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
      - Core, Fiscal Year 2000:
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
        - Internal Memos (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
        - Correspondence (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
        - Budget (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
      - Core, Fiscal Year 2001:
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
        - Internal Memos (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
        - Collateral Materials (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
        - Correspondence (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
        - Budget (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 2010.IA.21-01)
    - Florida Institute for Art Education (Florida State University):
      - Planning:
        - Internal Memos, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
        - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
        - Budget, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
        - Planning Grant Report, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
        - Grant Offer Letter, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
        - Review, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
        - Grant Proposal, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
        - Press, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
      - Implementation:
        - Year One:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Interim Report (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Site Visit, July 1988 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
        - Year Two:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Interim Report and Report #1 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Collateral Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Student Assessment Proposal & Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - [Loose Florida Summer Institute 1989 (two binders)] (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
        - Year Three:
          - Interim Report (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Collateral Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Interim Report, June 1990 (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-19)
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
        - Year Four:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Interim Report (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Collateral Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
        - Year Five:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Grant Offer Letter, May 5, 1993 (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Project Report for 1992 / Proposal for 1993 (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Interim Reports (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Collateral materials (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
        - Year Six:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Grant Offer Letter, October 14, 1993 (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Interim Reports (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Project Report for 1993 / Proposal for 1994 (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Collateral Materials (Summ. Institute) (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-20)
        - Year Seven:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - For Year 1995 Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Interim reports (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - For Year 1996/97 Core Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Collateral Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Core Program, 1996:
          - Internal memos (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - October Progress Report (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - December Progress Report (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Grant Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - April Progress Report (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - National Specialty Internal Memos/Correspondence/Proposal/Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Core Program, 1997:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Original & Revised for Year 1997 Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Interim Reports (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Core Program, 1998:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Fiscal Year 1999:
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Collateral Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
          - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
      - Strategic Planning Grant:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Grant Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - SPG Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Vision Statement (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Implementation Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Technical Assistance Visit (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
      - Florida Institute of Art Education (FIAE) Student Assessment:
        - Fiscal Year 1991, Year Three, Student Assessment Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Fiscal Year 1992, Year Four: Student Assessment Grant, Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Fiscal Year 1992, Year Four: Student Assessment Grant, Contract(s) (Box 2007.IA.16-21)
        - Fiscal Year 1993, Year Five: Student Assessment, Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Fiscal Year 1994, Year Six: Student Assessment Grant (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Fiscal Year 1994, Year Six: Student Assessment Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Fiscal Year 1995, Year Seven: Student Assessment Grant (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Fiscal Year 1995, Year Seven: Student Assessment, Contract (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Fiscal Year 1995, Year Seven: Phase I Assessment Grant Financial Report (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Fiscal Year 1996, Year Eight: Student Assessment Grant (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Fiscal Year 1997, Year Nine: Student Assessment Grant (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Fiscal Year 1998/99: Student Assessment Grant (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
      - Comprehensive Holistic Assessment Unit:
        - Mother's Helper (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Tar Beach (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Brooklyn Bridge (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Study for Painting with White Border (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Frank Lloyd Wright Fallingwater (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Still Life with Parrots (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - Shalako Mana Kachina (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - The Great Wave off Kanagawa (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
        - Leonardo DaVinci's Mona Lisa (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
        - Field Test Handbook (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
        - A Guide to the Development of Comprehensive, Holistic, Assessment Task Units (CHATS), December 1996 [2 copies] (Box 2007.IA.16-22)
      - Florida State University [original grant award letters], 1987-1998; (2 folders) (Box 2009.IA.38-01)
    - Kutztown University, Pennsylvania:
      - Planning:
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Grant Offer Letter (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Implementation (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
        - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-56)
      - Kutztown University [original grant award letters], 1987 (Box 2009.IA.38-02)
    - Minnesota Discipline-Based Art Education Consortium (University of Minnesota):
      - Planning:
        - Grant Offer Letter, May 4, 1987 (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
        - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
        - Correspondence (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
        - Budget (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
        - Planning Grant Report (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
        - Grant Proposal (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
        - Review (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
        - Press (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
      - Implementation:
        - Year One:
          - Grant Offer Letter 1/13/89 (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
          - Fiscal Agent (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
          - Interim Report (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
          - Miscellaneous (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
          - Collateral Materials (Box 2007.IA.16-23)
          - Internal Memos (Box 2007.IA.16-23)